I am sure we will be dragged into war
.  We are supposed to
go to war against Russia.  Never again.
And while it started back then as a child,
as a teenager, it has become part of our DNA
.  Absolutely never again
.  It was all so crazy,
I
really never could have imagined that it would develop back into this so quickly.
Why was war born?   Yes
why?  What has to happen to people for
them to go to war?
There must be circumstances, conditions
, that are capable of sending an entire
society into a state of emergency.
And today I experience this
repetition again, now even with the Russians in
our story, that they are supposed to be
the enemies again.  This is
pure psychiatry, this is pure
warning.
I remember when I was a young man and asked, "Well,
you all knew that, didn't you?"  No, we did
n't know that.  We knew
nothing about concentration camps or anything like that.  Yes, is that possible
?  But you really can't
say that anymore today.  We didn't know.
Hans Joachimz,
you know about the aftermath of war, are
you currently experiencing one before it personally?
Yes, unfortunately.
The answer came very quickly.   Yes
.  Yes, because that's the topic that's
currently
preoccupying me, especially towards the end of my life, something I never could have imagined
.  Uh, [clears throat]
I grew up in the
traumatization after the war and
post-war period, and practically never
again, and during the beginning, um, back then
as a child, as a teenager, it
became part of my DNA, so of course
never again.  It was all such
madness.
And
I really never would have imagined that things would develop so quickly again
.  Although, as a psychotherapist, I'll say it again:
I should have known
.
I knew it too.  I mean, when
I think about the books I've done
, like The False Life, The
Narcissistic Society, or
the last one, War Lust, Peace
Ability, and so on, I did them
because I knew, and this
could happen again at any time; it's
present in people.
And
that was the truly decisive experience I had to accept in the course of my life: that
after the war,
absolutely nothing was understood
about what drives people to war
, namely their inner psychological
situation.
Um,
it was a long internal process to have to
accept that this "never
again" has
never truly been understood
, that it is just propaganda, just
phrases, just to numb one's own
guilt.  So, the majority of
people were guilty of
National Socialism,
and
I think that
might also be a motive for
becoming a psychotherapist.  Um, to
understand what happened to the people
, also in the hope or
in the maintenance that this might not
happen to me.  I hope I don't
get into such waters.
Um, and yes, that has been on my mind, and the fact that
it's actually happening again now means
that I have to assume
, have to expect, that
at least
those who are in power want
and need war.  They want him because they
need him.
And this is how I explain it to myself.  So this
system, I'll call it
financial capitalist nomopathy,
a societal dysfunction
that is essentially
[sighs] ruled by money,
is in crisis or ultimately
over-indebted with insane
debts that can never be repaid, and the idea of
growth has
reached its limit – growth in
performance, success, and money. Above all,
the only way out
seems to be for those in
charge
to achieve temporary economic growth through war.  We are experiencing this right now.
German industry is downsizing.  Instead of
cars, tanks or weapons are being
built.  Something like that.  Um, as a last
resort, this rescue is an
unrealistic, insane rescue attempt,
that one is now practically
trying to keep the economy alive
by producing weapons.
Yes, weapons are a
wasted investment.  So, this offers
no added value whatsoever.  Uh, all you can do with it is
kill and destroy, and then
rebuild.  And this lazy trick
is perhaps the background of
an illusory, a mad
rescue
illusion, to first stabilize the system through war
, that is, to
gain the profit and then the
destruction, the killing, in order to
rebuild it, to start anew.
Mhm.  That was practically it, now
we were already outside.  Um,
yes, um, we are of course
also exploring the inner aspects here, that is, the internal
conditions that must be present where possible for
war to be possible, for
people to go to war.  Something
they've been dealing with for a very,
very long time.  Um, and
perhaps going back to this point again,
yes, they were born in 1943, so shortly
before the end of the war.  Um, that means
they
also experienced all this post-war trauma,
and it shaped them greatly
.  Um, her grandparents were
expelled and she says that
they never recovered from this trauma
.  And her grandmother had also
used this phrase I gave her.  Never
again war –
when she said it, it was no mere platitude.  Um,
[clears throat] do you really have to say that
she was wrong?
So,
it's more about the parents, or rather the
grandparents.  Yeah, right?  Yes.
Um, well,
I can't really say.  There was
no real, substantive, and understanding discussion with the parents and also with the parents' generation, i.e., the acquaintances who were in contact with the parents.  I still remember the
pressing questions I had as a teenager.
Why did you make war?  Why did
you participate?  What did you think, were you
Nazis?  Did you do anything about it?  There
were no real answers.  No,
we're not talking about that, and oh, just
leave it at that.  And so, um, I
'm back to my motive; then
I started
reading the philosophers, the uh, uh,
psychologists.  Um, I was
looking for answers that didn't exist.
They were therefore not available in the private sphere of
family and friends, and certainly
not in society.
So, why was war fought?
Yes, why, uh, what has to happen to people for
them to go to war?
One had the impression, as I
experienced it back then, that the Nazis had managed to create a situation where
a majority
enthusiastically went to war, finding it to be the
right thing to do.  Yes.  How much of it
was propaganda, I would
question again today, but
obviously, when you look at the pictures
, how people shouted "Heil Hitler"
and the enthusiasm of the masses,
and so, yes, I very soon
realized that this is a
societal disease, this is a
warning.  Um, there must be circumstances,
conditions, that
are capable of sending an entire society into a state of emergency
.  And, uh, I
only experienced that again in the GDR,
and I'm experiencing it again today.  Mm.  Well,
for me the fall of the Berlin Wall was of course a
very happy experience, finally
a chance for real democracy or something like that,
and a chance for her work too.
I mean, they couldn't
actually do that work there
, could they?  Yes.  and then the experience of
how the unification process
was carried out.  I coined
the term back then, namely an
interplay, a collusive
interplay as a collusion of
domination and subjugation.
So no unification has come about
, no unification that would allow for an understanding of
what went
well and what
went badly in the West, and what went well and badly in the GDR
.  It was a one-sided view that everything
in the West was only good, and in the East only bad,
and that was of course, uh, madness.  Yeah,
nonsense.  Yes. Yes.  And then, um, I
realized that the democracy we're
getting, which I had longed for so much
,
is also a mistake.  So,
submission to authority, that's not
democratic, that's a new
system of domination.
Uh, the West is only right and everything that
belongs to Western life is
only bad in the East.  And that
confirmed my opinion.  Even back in the
GDR days,
and as a teenager, I had been
dealing with
National Socialism and
kept asking myself, how can it
be, where have the Nazis suddenly gone
?  Yes, there were no more Nazis in the GDR
, until people realized that they had either joined
the SD or gone into hiding in the West
or something.  In the West it
soon became clear, yes, Nazis could
suddenly be in politics,
could even be in the judiciary, and yes,
how is that even possible?  So what about
the recurring question: what kind of
people are these?  So, they still have such a
political attitude, such a
mindset, today that they are even prepared to kill,
and tomorrow, ah,
now I'm different.  Yes, me, and I'll say something
different.  How does that work?  What?
So, yes, um, the question of the psychiatrist,
the psychotherapist, is: what is
going on in these souls?  Mhm.  So, to put it very
simply, emptied souls,
death souls, uh yes
, the emptied one perhaps, they
always fill themselves up as a substitute with whatever is
needed or